卢卡斯电影
很久以前，在遥远的银河系…
星球大战
帝国大反击
反抗军处于黑暗时期
帝国的死星战斗基地被毁
但反抗军也因秘密基地曝光
而四处逃窜
一群自由斗士
在卢克天行者领导下
建立了新的秘密基地
地点在冰冷遥远的霍斯星
为追捕卢克天行者
邪恶的黑武士达斯维达派出无数爪牙
遍寻银河每个角落…
回音三号呼叫七号
Echo Three to Echo Seven.
老韩，听到没？
Han, old buddy, do you read me?
清楚得很，干嘛？
Loud and clear, kid. What's up?
我兜了一圈,没发现生物迹象
I finished my circle. I don't pick up any life readings.
冰天雪地会有什么生物？
There isn't enough life on this ice cube to fill a space cruiser.
感应器装好了，我走了
The sensors are placed. I'm going back.
好，等会见
Right. I'll see you shortly.
这一带有陨石坠落
There's a meteorite that hit the ground near here.
我看看，马上就好
I want to check it out. It won't take long.
稳住
Steady.
稳住，怎么啦？有东西？
Steady, girl. What's the matter? You smell something?
阿秋，阿秋
Chewie. Chewie?
别发脾气
All right. Don't lose your temper.
我马上来帮你
I'll come right back and give you a hand.
苏洛
Solo.
没发现生命迹象，将军。感应器装好了
No sign of life out there, General. The sensors are in place.
- 有动静你会知道   - 天行者回来没有？
- You'll know if anything comes around. - Commander Skywalker reported in yet?
没有，他去看陨石
No. He's checking out a meteorite that hit near him.
这一带陨石太多，敌舰入侵很难发现
With all the meteor activity, it's gonna be difficult to spot approaching ships.
我得走了，不能再待了
General, I gotta leave. I can't stay any more.
- 很遗憾   - 贾霸悬赏抓我
- I'm sorry to hear that. - There's a price on my head.
再不拿钱给他，就死定了
If I don't pay off Jabba the Hutt, I'm a dead man.
有这个阴影确实不好
A death mark's not an easy thing to live with.
你是个勇士，很不舍得你走
You're a good fighter, Solo. I hate to lose you.
谢谢你，将军
Thank you, General.
公主殿下，就此别过
Well, Your Highness, guess this is it.
好
That's right.
别太难过，再会了，殿下
Don't get all mushy on me. So long, Princess.
老韩！
Han.
- 什么事，殿下？   - 你不是要留下吗？
- Yes, Your Highnessness. - I thought you had decided to stay.
到处有赏金猎人在找我，我不得不走
The bounty hunter we ran into in Ord Mantell changed my mind.
我们需要你
Han, we need you.
- “我们”？  - 对
- We need? - Yes.
- 不是“”需要？   - 我？
- What about you need? - I need?
我不明白
I don't know what you're talking about.
- 我想也是   - 我应该明白什么？
- You probably don't. - What precisely am I supposed to know?
别装了，对我有感觉，才要我留下来
Come on. You want me to stay because of the way you feel about me.
对，你是个好帮手，有领导才干
Yes. You're a great help to us. You're a natural leader.
不对！ 不是那个
No. That's not it.
来啊…
Come on.
- 招了吧   - 你在胡思乱想
- Come on. - You're imagining things.
是吗？那跟来干嘛？
Am I? Then why are you following me?
怕我不跟吻别？
Afraid I'd leave without giving you a goodbye kiss?
- 还不如去亲武技兽   - 我来安排
- I'd just as soon kiss a Wookiee. - I can arrange that.
你需要好好亲一下
You could use a good kiss!
怎么能怪我？又没叫你开电热器
Don't blame me. I didn't ask you to turn on the thermal heater.
我只说公主房间很冷
I merely commented that it was freezing in the princess's chamber.
但本来就该那样
It's supposed to be freezing.
她衣服都湿了，怎么办？
How we're going to dry her clothes I really don't know.
够了！
Oh, switch off!
现在拆开干嘛？都要走了！
Why did you take this apart now? I'm trying to get us out of here.
- 对不起…   - 装回去！
- Excuse me. - Put them back together right now.
- 有事跟您说   - 什么事？
- Might I have a word? - What do you want?
是莉亚公主，她想跟你通话
Princess Leia's been trying to get you on the communicator.
我对讲机关了，不想跟她讲话
I turned it off. I don't want to talk to her.
公主担心卢克主人，他没回来
Princess Leia is wondering about Master Luke. He hasn't come back.
- 也不知道在哪   - 我也不知道
- She doesn't know where he is. - I don't know where he is.
- 没有人知道   - 怎么说没人知道？
- Nobody knows where he is. - What do you mean, nobody knows?
值日官！
Deck Officer.
- 值日官！   - 对不起
- Deck Officer. - Excuse me, sir. Might I-
天行者在哪里？
Do you know where Commander Skywalker is?
没看见，有可能从南入口进来
I haven't seen him. It's possible he came in the south entrance.
有可能？打听一下好吗？
It's possible? Why don't you go find out?
- 天快黑了   - 是
- It's getting dark out there. - Yes, sir.
能不能请问怎么回事？
Excuse me, sir. Might I enquire what's going on?
- 要问就问   - 不可理喻
- Why not? - Impossible man.
走，R2，去找莉亚公主
Come along, R2. Let's find Princess Leia.
别跟人家说，我觉得主人出事了
Between ourselves, I think Master Luke is in considerable danger.
天行者没从南入口回来
Commander Skywalker hasn't come in the south entrance.
- 有可能忘了报到   - 不会，气垫车好了吗？
- Maybe he forgot to check in. - Not likely. Are the speeders ready?
改装还没完成
Not yet. We're having trouble adapting them to the cold.
- 那就骑咚咚兽   - 气温降得太快了
- We'll have to go out on tauntauns. - The temperature's dropping too rapidly.
而我的朋友还在外面
That's right, and my friend's out in it.
它没一会就会冻毙
Your tauntaun will freeze before you reach the first marker.
那就地狱再见
Then I'll see you in hell.
进去吧，R2
You must come along now, R2.
这样不是办法
There's really nothing more we can do.
我的关节快冻僵了
And my joints are freezing up.
别说傻话，少爷当然会回来
Don't say things like that. Of course we'll see Master Luke again.
他一定会平安无恙
And he'll be quite all right. You'll see.
真会胡思乱想，他一定会平安无恙
Stupid little short circuit. He'll be quite all right.
巡逻队都回来了，还是…
Sir, all the patrols are in. Still no-
还是没有发现
Still no contact from Skywalker or Solo.
莉亚公主，R2收不到任何信号
Mistress Leia, R2 says he's been quite unable to pick up any signals...
但有可能是距离的关系
although he admits that his own range is far too weak to abandon all hope.
殿下，今晚是没办法了
Your Highness, there's nothing more we can do tonight.
门屏必须关闭
The shield doors must be closed.
- 把门关上   - 是
- Close the doors. - Yes, sir.
R2说生还的希望是725比1
R2 says the chances of survival are 725-to-1.
其实，R2也曾失算
Actually, R2 has been known to make mistakes...
有的时候
from time to time.
真是的…
Oh, dear. Oh, dear.
别担心卢克主人，他一定会平安的
Don't worry about Master Luke. I'm sure he'll be all right.
以人的标准来说，他算聪明的
He's quite clever, you know, for a human being.
卢克…
Luke.
卢克
班？
Ben?
去达可巴星系
You will go to the Dagobah system.
达可巴星系？
Dagobah system?
去那里拜尤达为师
There you will learn from Yoda...
他是我的绝地师父
the Jedi master who instructed me.
别这样，给我个生命迹象
Don't do this, Luke. Give me a sign here.
- 没什么时间了   - 班…
- Not much time. - Ben.
撑着点，老弟
Hang on, kid.
达可巴星系，达可巴
Dagobah system. Dagobah.
这味道不好闻
This may smell bad, kid...
尤达…
Yoda.
但能让你保暖，我来搭遮棚
but it'll keep you warm till I get the shelter up.
--
Ben. Dagobah.
我以为这东西…
I thought they smelled bad...
只是表皮臭
on the outside.
回音基地，收到信号了
Echo Base, I've got something.
很微弱，但可能是生物
Not much, but it could be a life form.
天行者，听得见吗？
Commander Skywalker, do you copy?
这是野象二号
This is Rogue Two.
苏洛舰长，听得见吗？
Captain Solo, do you copy?
天行者，听见没有？
Commander Skywalker, do you copy?
这是野象二号
This is Rogue Two.
早安，谢谢来看我们
Good morning. Nice of you guys to drop by.
回音基地，这是野象二号
Echo Base, this is Rogue Two.
人找到了，再说一次，人找到了
I've found them. Repeat. I've found them.
主人，看你复元真高兴
Master Luke, sir, it's so good to see you fully functional again.
- 谢谢，3PO   - R2也松了一口气
- Thanks, 3PO. - R2 expresses his relief also.
怎么样？看样子还可以
How ya feelin', kid? You don't look so bad to me.
看来健康得不得了
You look strong enough to pull the ears off a gundark.
- 多亏你救了我   - 这是第二次了
- Thanks to you. - That's two you owe me, junior.
圣上
Well, Your Worship...
看样子我被留住了
looks like you managed to keep me around for a little while longer.
这跟我没关系
I had nothing to do with it.
赖将军说要等防护罩建构完成
General Rieekan thinks it's dangerous for any ships to leave...
才好让船舰离开
until we've activated the energy field.
这理由不错
That's a good story.
我想就是舍不得我
I think you just can't bear to let a gorgeous guy like me out of your sight.
你想象力可真丰富
I don't know where you get your delusions, laser brain.
你笑嘛，大毛球
Laugh it up, fuzzball...
你没看见我们在通道里
but you didn't see us alone in the south passage.
她对我表露真情
She expressed her true feelings for me.
什么？
My-
你这个傲慢、愚昧…
Why, you stuck-up, half-witted...
邋遢的野人！
scruffy-looking nerf herder!
说谁邋遢？
Who's scruffy-lookin'?
她一定是心事被我说中了
I must have hit close to the mark to get her riled up like that, huh, kid?
我看你不很了解女人
I guess you don't know everything about women yet.
总部人员，向指挥中心报到
Headquarters personnel, report to command centre.
保重
Take it easy.
失陪
Excuse us, please.
公主，有不速之客
Princess, we have a visitor.
在基地外，十二区往东移动
We picked up something outside Zone 12 moving east.
- 是金属品   - 那就不是那些怪兽
- It's metal. - It couldn't be one of those creatures.
- 可能是我们的气垫船   - 不对…等一下
- Could be one of our speeders. - No. Wait.
有个微弱信号
There's something very weak coming through.
我懂六百万种通讯方式
Sir, I am fluent in six million forms of communication.
反抗军不用这讯号，可能是帝国的通讯
This signal is not used by the Alliance. It could be an imperial code.
总之是敌非友，阿秋，去看看
It isn't friendly. Chewie, let's check it out.
派野象十、十一号查看，飞行员到三十八号棚报到
Send Rogues 10 and 11 to Station 38.
- 已经支离破碎   - 是什么东西？
- I'm afraid there's not much left. - What was it?
一种机器人，我只开了一枪
Droid of some kind. I didn't hit it that hard.
- 一定是有自爆装置   - 帝国的侦查机器人
- Must have had a self-destruct. - An imperial probe droid.
八成被他们发现了
It's a good bet the Empire knows we're here.
我们最好快撤离
We'd better start the evacuation.
- 将军   - 什么事，舰长？
- Admiral. - Yes, Captain?
好像有发现了。派去霍斯星系的机器人
I think we've got something, sir. The report is only a fragment...
提供了一点线索
from a probe droid in the Hoth system, but it's the best lead we've had.
派出的机器人有几千个
We have thousands of probe droids searching the galaxy.
- 我要证据，不要线索   - 有生物的迹象
- I want proof, not leads. - The visuals indicate life readings.
生物可多着呢，如果每个都追…
It could mean anything. If we followed up every lead-
霍斯星系 应无人烟
But, sir, the Hoth system is supposed to be devoid of humans forms.
- 有发现吗？   - 是，勋爵
- You found something? - Yes, my lord.
没错，叛党在那里
That's it. The rebels are there.
图上没有的聚落太多了
My lord, there are so many uncharted settlements.
- 可能是走私客…   - 就是那个星系
- It could be smugglers- - That is the system.
我相信天行者也在那里
And I'm sure Skywalker is with them.
飞往霍斯星系
Set your course for the Hoth system.
韦将军，叫部属准备
General Veers, prepare your men.
将军
Admiral.
七组和十组飞气垫船
Groups Seven and 10 will stay behind to fly the speeders.
每艘运输舰一装满
As soon as each transport is loaded...
管制台就会下令起飞
evacuation control will give clearance for launch.
是
Right, sir.
行了
All right. That's it.
试试看
Try it.
快关掉！关掉！
Turn it off! Turn it off!
T47撤离需要很久
Sir, it will take quite a while to evacuate the T-47 s.
重装备就算了，小型设备装运时间很多
Forget the heavy equipment. There's time to get small modules on the transports.
- 保重   - 谢谢
- Take care, sir. - Thanks.
阿秋，你多保重
Chewie, take care of yourself, okay?
--
Okay, okay.
老弟
Hi, kid.
一定有原因，另一边看看
There's gotta be a reason for it. Check it at the other end.
等一下
Wait a second.
- 你还好吧？   - 还好
- Are you all right? - Yeah.
小心
Be careful.
你也是
You too.
将军，星际驱逐舰队
General, there's a fleet of Stardestroyers...
刚脱离超太空
coming out of hyperspace in Sector Four.
所有电力转到防护罩
Reroute all power to the energy shield.
要让运输舰安然离开
We gotta hold them till all transports are away.
准备地面作战
Prepare for ground assault.
- 什么事，将军？   - 舰队停止了光速飞行
- What is it, General? - The fleet has moved out of light speed.
霍斯星系第六星球…
ComScan has detected an energy field...
有个地区受强大防护罩保护
protecting an area of the sixth planet of the Hoth system.
足以抵抗任何轰炸
The field is strong enough to deflect any bombardment.
叛军知道我们到了
The rebels are alerted to our presence.
欧将军早该停止光速飞行
Admiral Ozzel came out of light speed too close to the system.
他想施行突击…
He felt surprise was wiser.
他既笨拙又愚蠢
He is as clumsy as he is stupid.
将军，准备地面攻击
General, prepare your troops for a surface attack.
是
Yes, my lord.
维达勋爵
Lord Vader.
我们已停止光速飞行…
The fleet has moved out of light speed, and we're preparing to-
这是你最后一次犯错
You have failed me for the last time, Admiral.
- 皮舰长   - 是
- Captain Piett. - Yes, my lord?
让部队在防护罩外登陆
Make ready to land our troops beyond their energy field...
别让叛党离开这个星系
and deploy the fleet so that nothing gets off the system.
现在由你指挥，皮将军
You are in command now, Admiral Piett.
谢谢，维达勋爵
Thank you, Lord Vader.
运兵舰在北门集合
All troop carriers will assemble at the north entrance.
大型运输舰装满就出发
The heavy transport ships will leave as soon as they're loaded.
每艘由两架战机护航
Only two fighter escorts per ship.
防护罩开启时间有限
The energy shield can only be opened for a short time...
你们要紧跟着运输舰
so you'll have to stay very close to your transports.
两架对一艘驱逐舰？
Two fighters against a Stardestroyer?
离子炮会不时发射
The ion cannon will fire several shots...
使敌舰远离你们航道
to make sure that any enemy ships will be out of your flight path.
离开防护罩后
When you've gotten past the energy shield...
直接前往会合点
proceed directly to the rendezvous point.
明白？
Understood?
祝好运
Good luck.
各就各位，走吧
Everybody to your stations. Let's go.
他们会先破坏发电机
Their primary target will be the power generators.
准备开启防护罩
Prepare to open shield.
长官，叛军舰艇接近了
Sir, rebel ships are coming into our sector.
好，第一批客人上门
Good. Our first catch of the day.
离子炮准备
Stand by, ion control.
发射
Fire.
第一艘运输舰安全了
The first transport is away.
觉得怎么样？
Feeling all right, sir?
好得很，戴克，你呢？
Just like new, Dak. How about you?
我感觉勇气十足
Right now I feel I could take on the whole Empire myself.
我了解
I know what you mean.
-3T8回音站，发现帝国装甲走兽
Echo Station 3-T8. We've spotted imperial walkers.
北脊有装甲走兽
Imperial walkers on the north ridge.
-57回音站，我们来了
Echo Station 57, we're on our way.
大家靠近点
All right, boys, keep tight now.
卢克，我的攻击路径没设好
Luke, I have no approach vector. I'm not set.
慢慢来，戴克
Steady, Dak.
三角攻击队形，开始
Attack pattern Delta. Go now.
好，我来了
I'm coming in.
郝碧，你没问题吧？
Hobbie, you still with me?
装甲太厚了
That armour's too strong for blasters.
发射绳钩，把它们绊倒
Rogue Group, use your harpoons and tow cables.
钩它们的腿，可能只有这办法
Go for the legs. It might be our only chance.
准备，戴克
Stand by, Dak.
卢克，射控出了问题
Luke, we've got a malfunction in fire control.
要用辅助系统
I'll have to cut in the auxiliary.
撑一下
Just hang on.
等一下，戴克。准备发射绳钩
Hang on, Dak. Get ready to fire that tow cable.
戴克
Dak?
维达勋爵，我已接近主发电机
Yes, Lord Vader. I've reached the main power generators.
防护罩即将关闭，可以开始登陆
The shield will be down in moments. You may start your landing.
野象三号
Rogue Three.
听到了，领队
Copy, Rogue Leader.
魏吉，我的炮手阵亡了 你来射这一枪
Wedge, I've lost my gunner. You'll have to make this shot.
我帮你掩护
I'll cover for you.
准备绳钩，跟我飞过去
Set your harpoon. Follow me on the next pass.
我过来了，领队
Coming around, Rogue Leader.
稳住，野象二号
Steady, Rogue Two.
发射绳钩
Activate harpoon.
射得好，詹生
Good shot,Janson.
再绕一次，来了
One more pass.
缆绳出尽，让它去吧
Cable out. Let her go!
放掉缆绳
Detach cable.
放掉了
Cable detached.
快！
Come on!
- 这下倒了   - 我看到了，魏吉，做得好
- That got him! - I see it, Wedge. Good work.
没法一次保护两艘运输舰
I don't think we can protect two transports at a time.
时间所剩不多
It's risky, but we can't hold out much longer.
只能这么办
We have no choice.
- 巡逻艇出发   - 撤离剩余人员
- Launch patrol. - Evacuate remaining ground staff.
这个装那里 那个装那里，懂吗？
This one goes there, that one goes there. Right?
R2，好好照顾主人，听到没？
R2, you take good care of Master Luke now, understand?
也要照顾自己
And do take good care of yourself.
唉，真是的
Oh, dear. Oh, dear.
部队全部登陆攻击
All troops will debark for ground assault.
准备射击主发电机
Prepare to target the main generator.
- 野象二号，没事吧？   - 没事，我跟着你，领队
- Rogue Two, are you all right? - Yeah. I'm with you, Rogue Leader.
准备绳钩，我掩护你
Set harpoon. I'll cover for you.
- 我来了   - 小心炮火
- Coming around. - Watch that crossfire, boys.
设定第三位置
Set for position three.
稳着
Steady.
紧跟着低飞
Stay tight and low. This is it!
郝碧
Hobbie!
我中弹了
I've been hit!
- 没事吧？   - 怎么还没走？
- You all right? - Why are you still here?
- 我听说指挥中心被击中   - 刚才就叫你走了
- Heard the command centre had been hit. - You've got your clearance to leave.
别担心，我会走。我先送你们上去
Don't worry. I'll leave. First I'm gonna get you to your ship.
殿下，只剩这艘运输舰了 这是唯一的希望
Your Highness, we must take this last transport. It's our only hope.
派12区的部队到南坡 负责保护战机
Send all troops in Sector 12 to the south slope to protect the fighters.
帝国部队进了基地，
Imperial troops have entered the base.
帝国部队…
Imperial troops have entered-
快走
Come on. That's it.
下达撤退信号
Give the evacuation code signal.
快上运输舰
And get to your transports.
等等我…
Wait for me.
开始撤退
Begin retreat!
回去！
Fall back!
- 发电机距离   - 17.28
- Distance to power generators? - 17.28.
瞄准，全部火力
Target. Maximum firepower.
运输舰，我是苏洛，快起飞，我没法过来
Transport, this is Solo. Take off. I can't get to you.
我带公主搭千年鹰号
I'll get her out on the Falcon. Come on.
你们去哪里？ 回来！
Where are you going? Come back!
等等我…站住
Wait! Wait for me! Stop!
- 每次都这样！   - 快
- How typical. - Come on.
快点，金童子！你要变永久居民了
Hurry up, goldenrod! You're gonna be a permanent resident.
等一下…
Wait! Wait!
- 怎么啦？  - 要不要我下去推？
- How's this? - Would it help if I got out and pushed?
- 苏洛舰长…   - 会有帮助
- Captain Solo. Captain Solo. - It might.
我想跟你说…
Sir, might I suggest that you-
等一下好了
It can wait.
这艘破船哪能跑得了？
This bucket of bolts will never get past that blockade.
这宝贝有几招还没使呢
This baby's got a few surprises left in her.
快点…
Come on! Come on!
开机，希望不要熄火
Switch over. Let's hope we don't have a burnout.
看吧
See?
你总有一天会出错，我希望能够目睹
Someday you'll be wrong. I hope I'm there to see it.
加速！
Punch it!
R2
R2.
准备起飞
Get her ready for take-off.
祝好运，卢克，在会合点见
Good luck, Luke. See you at the rendezvous.
别担心，R2，我们要走了
Don't worry, R2. We're going. We're going.
没问题，我在设新的航线
There's nothing wrong, R2. I'm just setting a new course.
我们不跟他们会合，要去达可巴星系
We're not gonna regroup with the others. We're going to the Dagobah system.
对，R2
Yes, R2.
没关系，暂时还是用手动飞行
That's all right. I'd like to keep it on manual control for a while.
- 我看见了   - 看见什么了？
- I saw 'em! I saw 'em! - Saw what?
两艘星际驱逐舰过来了
Stardestroyers, two of'em coming right at us.
- 先生，有件事情…   - 叫它闭嘴，不然就关机
- Sir, might I suggest- - Shut him up or shut him down!
检查反射屏
Check the deflector shield.
好极了，我们可以摆脱他们
Great. Well, we can still outmanoeuvre them.
采取闪避行动
Take evasive action!
- 准备以光速飞行   - 可是…
- Prepare to jump to light speed. - But, sir!
他们接近了
They're getting closer.
是吗？ 瞧我的
Oh, yeah? Watch this.
瞧什么？
Watch what?
- 麻烦大了   ----
- I think we're in trouble. - If I may say so...
我刚才就发现启动器坏了
I noticed earlier the hyperdrive motivator has been damaged.
- 没法用光速飞行   - 麻烦大了
- It's impossible to go to light speed. - We're in trouble.
检查平面辅助仪
Horizontal boosters!
缓冲器
Alluvial dampers.
不对，液压扳手给我
That's not it. Bring me the hydrospanner.
这下我也没办法了
I don't know how we're gonna get out of this one.
阿秋！
Chewie!
不是雷射炮，被撞到了
That wasn't a laser blast. Something hit us.
老韩，快上来
Han, get up here.
快，阿秋
Come on, Chewie!
小行星群
Asteroids.
- 阿秋，定位271   - 你在干嘛？
- Chewie, set 271. - What are you doing?
你要开进小行星群？
You're not actually going into an asteroid field?
那他们就不敢追了，对不对？
They'd be crazy to follow us, wouldn't they?
不必这样讨好我
You don't have to do this to impress me.
成功穿越小行星群的机率
Sir, the possibility of successfully navigating an asteroid field...
- 是3700比1   - 别跟我谈机率
- is approximately 3,720-to-1. - Never tell me the odds.
说想看我犯错，机会可能来了
You said you wanted to be around when I made a mistake. This could be it.
我把话收回
I take it back.
再不出去会被撞个粉碎
We're gonna get pulverized if we stay out here much longer.
- 这点我同意   - 粉碎？
- Ain't gonna argue with that. - Pulverized?
我要去靠近一个大的
I'm going closer to one of the big ones.
- 靠近？   - 靠近？
- Closer? - Closer?
这等于自杀，无路可走了
This is suicide! There's nowhere to go.
那里，看来还可以
There. That looks pretty good.
什么看来还可以？
What looks pretty good?
对，很理想
Yeah. That'll do nicely.
对不起，我们去哪里？
Excuse me, ma'am, but where are we going?
希望你有把握
I hope you know what you're doing.
我也希望如此
Yeah. Me too.
对，达可巴星系到了
Yep, that's it. Dagobah.
不，我不会改变主意
No, I'm not gonna change my mind about this.
没有城市或科技的讯号
I'm not picking up any cities or technology.
但充满生命迹象
Massive life form readings though.
底下有生物
There's something alive down there.
我相信机器人会很安全
Yes. I'm sure it's perfectly safe for droids.
--
I know! I know!
我知道观测仪坏了，什么都看不见
All the scopes are dead. I can't see a thing.
我要准备降落了
Just hang on. I'm gonna start the landing cycle.
R2你别动，我来看看
No, R2, you stay put. I'll have a look around.
R2？
R2?
你在哪里？
Where are you?
R2！
R2!
小心一点
You be more careful.
R2…那边
R2, that way.
R2！
R2!
糟糕…
Oh, no.
你没事吧？ 来！
Are you all right? Come on.
还好你不太好吃
You were lucky to get out of there.
有没有哪里坏了？
Anything broken?
我不得不同意
If you're saying coming here was a bad idea...
的确不该来这里
I'm beginning to agree with ya.
R2，我们在干嘛？
R2, what are we doing here?
好像是…
It's like...
梦境的东西
something out of a dream or-
我也不知道
I don't know.
也许我发神经了
Maybe I'm just going crazy.
什么事，将军？
Yes, Admiral?
发现千年鹰了
Our ships have sighted the Millennium Falcon, lord...
但它进了小行星群…
but it has entered an asteroid field, and we cannot risk-
我不管
Asteroids do not concern me, Admiral.
- 我要逮到他们，不要借口   - 是
- I want that ship, not excuses. - Yes, lord.
只留下紧急供电系统
I'm gonna shut down everything but the emergency power systems.
我很不想问…会不会把我也关了？
Sir, I'm almost afraid to ask, but does that include shutting me down too?
我需要你跟计算机沟通
No. I need you to talk to the Falcon...
看超级加速器怎么了
find out what's wrong with the hyperdrive.
这个小行星可能不稳定
Sir, it's quite possible this asteroid is not entirely stable.
不稳定？
Not entirely stable?
你真会叫人安心
I'm glad you're here to tell us these things.
阿秋，带这教授到后头检查加速器
Chewie, take the professor in the back and plug him into the hyperdrive.
我有时真不懂人类
Sometimes I just don't understand human behaviour.
我只是尽我的责任
After all, I'm only trying to do my job.
放手
Let go.
- 请你放手   - 别那么兴奋
- Let go, please. - Don't get excited.
这样就能让我兴奋？
Captain, being held by you isn't quite enough to get me excited.
抱歉
Sorry, sweetheart.
也没时间做别的
I haven't got time for anything else.
要充电了？好
Ready for some power? Okay.
我看看…
Let's see now.
这样子…好了
Put that in there. There you go.
现在得找尤达
Now all I gotta do is find this Yoda...
要是有这号人物
if he even exists.
这里会有绝地大师吗？
It's really a strange place to find a Jedi master.
让我毛骨悚然
This place gives me the creeps.
但是…
Still...
好像又有点眼熟
there's something familiar about this place.
我也不知道，
I don't know.
- 好像…   - 好像什么？
- I feel like- - Feel like what?
好像有人在监视
Like we're being watched.
别动武器，我没有恶意
Away put your weapon. I mean you no harm.
我只是好奇…你来做什么？
I am wondering, why are you here?
- 我来找人   - 找人？
- I'm looking for someone. - Looking?
找到人了吧？
Found someone you have, I would say.
对
Right.
我可以帮你
Help you I can. Yes.
我看不行
I don't think so.
我找一个伟大的战士
I'm looking for a great warrior.
伟大的战士？
Great warrior.
战争不会使人伟大
Wars not make one great.
别动那个
Put that down.
那是我的晚餐
Hey! That's my dinner.
你吃这玩意，还长这么大？
How you get so big eating food of this kind?
我们不小心降落在水里
Listen, friend, we didn't mean to land in that puddle.
宇宙飞船出不来…
If we could get our ship out, we would. But we can't.
出不来
Aw, cannot get your ship out.
你快走吧
Get out of there.
不，会被你弄坏
Hey, you could have broken this.
别那样
Don't do that.
弄得乱七八糟
You're making a mess.
快给我
Hey, give me that.
给我，不然不帮你
Mine, or I will help you not.
我不要你帮忙，把灯还给我
I don't want your help. I want my lamp back.
我要用它来脱离这烂泥坑
I'm gonna need it to get out of this slimy mud-hole.
烂泥坑？这是我的家
Mud-hole? Slimy? My home this is.
R2，给他算了
R2, let him have it.
- 是我的！ 我的！  - R2
- Mine! Mine! Mine! - R2.
走了吧，小家伙，我们忙得很
Will you move along, little fella? We got a lot of work to do.
不，我要留下来帮你，帮你找朋友
Stay and help you I will. Find your friend.
我不是找朋友 我找一个绝地大师
I'm not looking for a friend. I'm looking for a Jedi master.
绝地大师尤达
Jedi master. Yoda.
- 你要找尤达   - 你认识他？
- You seek Yoda. - You know him?
嗯，我带你去找他
Take you to him I will.
对，但先去吃东西，来
Yes, yes, but now we must eat.
好吃的，来
Come. Good food. Come.
来啊
Come, come.
R2
R2...
你留着看东西
stay and watch after the camp.
R2死哪去了？
Where is R2 when I need him?
您的计算机使用的方言
Sir, I don't know where your ship learned to communicate...
我实在有听没懂
but it has the most peculiar dialect.
好像负电轴耦合器坏了
I believe it says the power coupling on the negative axis has been polarized.
恐怕要换掉
I'm afraid you'll have to replace it.
当然要换掉
Well, of course I'll have to replace it.
阿秋
Here. And, Chewie...
换一个负电轴耦合器
I think we better replace the negative power coupling.
圣上，我只是想帮忙
Hey, Your Worship, I'm only trying to help.
别那样叫我
Would you please stop calling me that?
好啊，莉亚
Sure, Leia.
- 有时你真是难相处   - 一点没错
- You make it so difficult sometimes. - I do. I really do.
可以温柔一点
You could be a little nicer though.
有时觉得我还不错
Admit it. Sometimes you think I'm all right.
有时候…也许
Occasionally, maybe...
如果你不无赖的话
when you aren't acting like a scoundrel.
无赖？
Scoundrel?
这字眼满好听的
I like the sound of that.
- 别那样   - 别怎样？
- Stop that. - Stop what?
别那样，我的手很脏
Stop that. My hands are dirty.
我的手也脏，怕什么？
My hands are dirty too. What are you afraid of?
- 怕？   - 在发抖
- Afraid? - You're trembling.
没有
I'm not trembling.
喜欢我无赖
You like me because I'm a scoundrel.
难得碰到无赖
There aren't enough scoundrels in your life.
我喜欢好人
I happen to like nice men.
- 我是个好人   - 你不是
- I'm a nice man. - No, you're not.
先生，我…
Sir, sir!
坏掉的耦合器找到了
I've isolated the reverse power flux coupling.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 真是多谢   - 您千万别客气
- Thank you very much. - You're perfectly welcome, sir.
那是他们最后一次出现
That, Lord Vader, was the last time they appeared in any of our scopes.
我们都这么惨，他们一定活不了
Considering the damage we've sustained, they must have been destroyed.
不，他们还活着
No, Captain, they're alive.
出动所有舰艇，要搜遍小行星群
I want every ship available to sweep the asteroid field until they are found.
- 维达勋爵   - 什么事？
- Lord Vader. - Yes, Admiral. What is it?
皇上请您跟他联系
The emperor commands you to make contact with him.
到小行星群外头
Move the ship out of the asteroid field...
免得信号受干扰
so that we can send a clear transmission.
是
Yes, my lord.
主人有何吩咐？
What is thy bidding, my master?
原力有了很大的纷扰
There is a great disturbance in the Force.
我也有感觉
I have felt it.
我们有个新敌人
We have a new enemy-
就是那个摧毁死星的年轻叛军
the young rebel who destroyed the Death Star.
我很确定这个男孩
I have no doubt this boy...
是安纳金天行者的后代
is the offspring of Anakin Skywalker.
这是不可能的
How is that possible?
你自己用心想想，黑武士
Search your feelings, Lord Vader.
就会知道这千真万确
You will know it to be true.
他能毁掉我们
He could destroy us.
他只是个孩子
He's just a boy.
欧比王已帮不了他
Obi-Wan can no longer help him.
他的原力很强
The Force is strong with him.
不能让他成为绝地武士
The son of Skywalker must not become a Jedi.
他能投效
If he could be turned...
帝国就好了
he would become a powerful ally.
是啊
Yes.
我们会如虎添翼
He would be a great asset.
能不能办到？
Can it be done?
他不投效，就死路一条
He will join us or die, master.
我相信很好吃，但为何不能先见尤达？
I'm sure it's delicious. I just don't understand why we can't see Yoda now.
要有耐心，绝地武士也该吃饭
Patience. For the Jedi, it is time to eat as well.
吃啊
Eat. Eat.
烫！
Hot.
好吃吧？
Good food. Good.
尤达住多远？去那里要很久吗？
How far away is Yoda? Will it take us long to get there?
不远，尤达不远
Not far. Yoda not far.
耐心，很快就见面了
Patience. Soon you will be with him.
根叶菜，我煮的
Root leaf. I cook.
你为何想当武士？
Why wish you become Jedi?
主要受我父亲影响
Mostly 'cause of my father, I guess.
啊，父亲…他非常厉害
Father. Powerful Jedi was he.
- 很厉害的武士   - 算了吧
- Powerful Jedi. - Oh, come on.
你哪会认识他？你连我都不认识
How could you know my father? You don't even know who I am.
我在干嘛？简直浪费时间
I don't even know what I'm doing here. We're wasting our time!
我没法教他
I cannot teach him.
这孩子没耐心
The boy has no patience.
他会学习忍耐
He will learn patience.
他心中充满怒气
Much anger in him...
跟他父亲一样
like his father.
我当时还不是一样？
Was I any different when you taught me?
--
No.
- 他时候还没到   - 尤达！
- He is not ready. - Yoda.
我时候到了…
I am ready.
班，我可以当武士。班，你跟他说…
I can be a Jedi. Ben, tell him I'm-
你时候到了？你知道什么？
Ready, are you? What know you ready?
我授徒已经八百年
For 800 years have I trained Jedi.
行不行，我自有定见
My own counsel will I keep on who is to be trained.
武士要有绝对的决心
AJedi must have the deepest commitment...
最严肃的态度
the most serious mind.
这个我观察很久了
This one a long time have I watched.
他一辈子都在
All his life has he looked away...
往远处看
to the future, to the horizon.
就是不肯脚踏实地
Never his mind on where he was...
把眼前的事做好
what he was doing.
就爱冒险
Adventure.
找刺激
Excitement.
武士不搞这些的
AJedi craves not these things.
你很卤莽
You are reckless.
我以前也是
So was I, if you remember.
他太老了
He is too old.
对，现在开始太晚了
Yes, too old to begin the training.
但我学了好多
But I've learned so much.
- 他能有始有终吗？   - 我不会让你失望
- Will he finish what he begins? - I won't fail you.
我不怕
I'm not afraid.
你会怕的
You will be.
- 请容我建议…   - 我不想听你建议
- Sir, if I may venture an opinion- - I'm not interested in your opinion.
外头有东西
There's something out there.
- 哪里？   - 在外面山洞里
- Where? - Outside in the cave.
那里，你听
There it is. Listen!
- 我出去看看   - 你疯啦？
- I'm going out there. - Are you crazy?
这玩意儿刚修好，不能让人拆了
I just got this bucket together. I won't let it get torn apart.
那我跟你去
Then I'm going with you.
我想我最好守着宇宙飞船
I think it might be better if I stay behind and guard the ship.
糟了…
Oh, no.
这地面好奇怪
This ground sure feels strange.
好像不是岩石
It doesn't feel like rock.
湿气好重
There's an awful lot of moisture in here.
搞不清楚，总觉得不对劲
I don't know. I have a bad feeling about this.
对
Yeah.
小心！
Watch out!
没事，没事
It's all right. It's all right.
我就知道，太空蝙蝠
Yeah, that's what I thought- mynock.
阿秋，检查一下
Chewie, check the rest of the ship and make sure there are no more attached...
别让它们咬电线
chewing on the power cables.
太空蝙蝠？
Mynocks?
进去，还有的话就赶走
Go inside. We'll clean them off if there are any more.
快走开！
Go away! Go away, beastly thing! Shoo!
等一下…
Wait a minute.
- 阿秋，我们走！   - 帝国舰队还在外面，这样出去不好…
- Chewie, let's get out of here! - The Empire is still out there!
没时间开会了
No time to discuss this in committee!
我没说要开会！
I am not a committee!
这里不能用光速
You can't make the jump to light speed in this asteroid field.
坐下，甜心，要起飞了
Sit down, sweetheart. We're taking off.
- 看！   - 我看见了
- Look! - I see it.
- 我们完了  - 山洞要垮了
- We're doomed! - The cave is collapsing.
- 这不是山洞   - 什么？
- This is no cave. - What?
对，快跑
Yes, run.
对
Yes.
武士的力量来自于原力
AJedi's strength flows from the Force.
但要注意黑暗面的势力，愤怒、恐惧、侵略心
But beware of the dark side. Anger, fear, aggression-
这就是原力的黑暗面
The dark side of the Force are they.
它在你战斗时，会很快到你心里
Easily they flow, quick to join you in a fight.
一旦走入歧途
If once you start down the dark path...
它就会主宰你的命运
forever will it dominate your destiny.
它会把你吞噬，就像欧比王的徒弟
Consume you it will, as it did Obi-Wan's apprentice.
黑武士
Vader.
- 黑暗面比较强吗？  - 不…
- Is the dark side stronger? - No, no.
只是较快，较容易、诱惑力较大
Quicker, easier, more seductive.
我如何分辨好坏？
How am I to know the good side from the bad?
你自然会知道
You will know...
你平静、沉寂的时候
when you are calm, at peace...
--
passive.
武士用原力来学习和防身
AJedi uses the Force for knowledge and defence...
而不是攻击
never for attack.
- 为什么不能…  - 不，别问
- But tell me why I can't- - No. There is no why.
今天到此为止
Nothing more will I teach you today.
别再想这些问题
Clear your mind of questions.
有点不对劲
There's something not right here.
好冷
I feel cold.
- 死亡   - 在那个地方…
- Death. - That place...
原力的黑暗面很强
is strong with the dark side of the Force.
那是邪恶的境地
A domain of evil it is.
你得进去
In you must go.
里头有什么？
What's in there?
只有你所带去的
Only what you take with you.
你的武器
Your weapons...
你不用带着
you will not need them.
赏金猎人！谁需要这些人渣？
Bounty hunters. We don't need their scum.
- 是的，长官   - 那些叛党跑不了
- Yes, sir. - Those rebels won't escape us.
“复仇者”号有重要讯息
Sir, we have a priority signal from the Stardestroyer Avenger.
好
Right.
找到千年鹰的有重赏
There will be a substantial reward for the one who finds the Millennium Falcon.
什么招式都可以用
You are free to use any methods necessary...
但我要活口
but I want them alive.
不要断手断脚
No disintegrations.
- 悉听尊便   - 维达勋爵
- As you wish. - Lord Vader.
大人，有发现了
My lord, we have them.
终于脱离小行星群了
Thank goodness we're coming out of the asteroid field.
我们快闪，准备光速飞行
Let's get out of here. Ready for light speed?
一！二！
One, two...
三！
three!
怎么这样？
It's not fair.
电路全都正常，这不能怪我！
Transfer circuits aren't working. It's not my fault.
- 不能用光速？   - 不是我的错
- No light speed? - It's not my fault.
后面的主反射屏没了
Sir, we just lost the main rear deflector shield.
舰尾再中弹，我们就完了
One more direct hit on the back quarter and we're done for.
掉头
Turn her around.
我说掉头！电力全转到前反射屏
Turn her around! I'm gonna put all power in the front shield.
- 你要攻击他们？  - 正面攻击驱逐舰
- You're gonna attack? - The odds of surviving...
还能全身而退的机率…
a direct assault on an imperial Stardestroyer-
闭嘴！
Shut up!
他们敢攻击我们！
They're moving to attack position.
立起反射屏
Shields up.
追踪，他们可能掉头再来
Track them. They may come around for another pass.
倪舰长，侦测仪上看不到了
Captain Needa, the ship no longer appears on our scopes.
不可能，它不可能有隐蔽装置
They can't have disappeared. No ship that small has a cloaking device.
- 但它失去了踪影  - 维达勋爵要知道情况
- There's no trace of them. - Captain, Lord Vader demands an update.
准备交通艇
Get a shuttle ready.
我要负起丢人的责任，向大臣道歉
I shall assume full responsibility for losing them and apologize to Lord Vader.
- 你们继续扫描   - 是，倪舰长
- Meanwhile, continue to scan the area. - Yes, Captain Needa.
用原力
Use the Force.
对
Yes.
移动石块
Now, the stone.
用感觉
Feel it.
集中精神！
Concentrate!
这下永远没救了
Oh, no. We'll never get it out now.
你好肯定
So certain are you.
你老是说没办法
Always with you it cannot be done.
你不懂我的话吗？
Hear you nothing that I say?
师父，石头是一回事
Master, moving stones around is one thing.
这可完全不同
This is totally different.
没什么不同
No. No different.
只是你觉得不同
Only different in your mind.
你要忘掉以前所学
You must unlearn what you have learned.
- 好吧，我试试看   - 不对，不要“试”
- All right. I'll give it a try. - Try not.
要“做”
Do...
否则就别做
or do not.
没什么试不试的
There is no try.
没办法，太大了
I can't. It's too big.
大小不是问题
Size matters not.
你看我，你看我不起眼，对不对？
Look at me. Judge me by my size, do you?
这样你就错了
And well you should not...
我有原力来帮助我
for my ally is the Force.
它是莫大的助力
And a powerful ally it is.
生命创造了原力
Life creates it...
让它壮大
makes it grow.
它的能量围绕着我们
Its energy surrounds us...
维系着我们
and binds us.
我们是聪明的生物，不是粗糙的东西
Luminous beings are we, not this crude matter.
你要感觉周围的原力
You must feel the Force around you.
这里，在你我之间
Here, between you, me...
那棵树，石头
the tree, the rock-
无所不在
everywhere.
对
Yes...
甚至在土地和宇宙飞船之间
even between the land and the ship.
这是强人所难
You want the impossible.
我…我不敢相信
I don't believe it.
所以你会失败
That is why you fail.
我接受你的道歉，倪舰长
Apology accepted, Captain Needa.
大臣，我们搜遍了，毫无发现
Lord Vader, our ships have completed their scan and found nothing.
他们若用光速
If the Millennium Falcon went into light speed...
早已跑远了
it'll be on the other side of the galaxy now.
通报各指挥部
Alert all commands.
注意他们可能的航向
Calculate every possible destination along their last known trajectory.
- 是，他们跑不了   - 别再让我失望
- Yes, my lord. We'll find them. - Don't fail me again...
将军
Admiral.
通报各指挥部，快部署
Alert all commands. Deploy the fleet.
苏洛舰长，这回太夸张了
Captain Solo, this time you have gone too far.
我就不闭嘴，秋巴卡。怎么就没人听我的？
I will not be quiet, Chewbacca. Why doesn't anyone listen to me?
舰队要散开了
The fleet's beginning to break up.
到后头准备脱离
Go stand by the manual release for the landing claw.
这样有什么用呢？
I really don't see how that's going to help.
在特别情况下，投降是很正常的事
Surrender is a perfectly acceptable alternative in extreme circumstances.
他们可能会…
The Empire may be gracious enough-
- 谢了   - 下一步怎么办？
- Thank you. - What did you have in mind next?
若按照正常程序，他们会先丢垃圾
If they follow standard imperial procedure...
才开始光速飞行
they'll dump their garbage before they go to light speed.
- 我们就可以飘开   - 跟垃圾一起
- Then we just float away. - With the rest of the garbage.
然后呢？
Then what?
在附近找个落脚地
Then we gotta find a safe port somewhere around here.
有哪里可去？
Any ideas?
- 这是哪里？   - 安诺亚星系
- Where are we? - The Anoat system.
安诺亚没地方可去
The Anoat system. There's not much there.
对，等一下…有意思
Oh, wait. This is interesting.
- 蓝多！   - 蓝多星系？
- Lando. - Lando system?
不，蓝多是个人，蓝多卡瑞辛
Lando's not a system. He's a man. Lando Calrissian.
他爱打牌、赌博
Card player, gambler.
- 十足无赖，正对你味口   - 谢了
- A scoundrel. You'd like him. - Thanks.
在贝斯平，满远的，但我们到得了
Bespin. It's pretty far, but I think we can make it.
- 采矿区？   - 对，提班纳瓦斯
- A mining colony? - Yeah, a tibanna gas mine.
蓝多跟人家骗来的
Lando conned somebody out of it.
他跟我是老交情
We go back a long way, Lando and me.
- 能信任他吗？   - 不
- Can you trust him? - No.
但是他痛恨帝国
But he's got no love for the Empire. I can tell you that.
阿秋，准备，脱离
Here we go, Chewie. Stand by. Detach.
你有时很英明
You do have your moments.
难得一次，但还算不错
Not many of them, but you do have them.
集中精神
Concentrate.
感觉原力的流动
Feel the Force flow.
对了
Yes.
好
Good.
冷静
Calm.
对
Yes.
透过原力，会看见一些东西
Through the Force, things you will see.
别的地方，未来、过去
Other places. The future. The past.
早已不在的朋友
Old friends long gone.
要控制
Control, control.
你要学着控制
You must learn control.
我看见…一座城市在云间
I saw a city in the clouds.
你在那里有朋友
Friends you have there.
- 他们在受苦   - 你看到的是未来
- They were in pain. - It is the future you see.
未来？
Future?
他们会不会死？
Will they die?
很难说
Difficult to see.
未来总是在变
Always in motion is the future.
我要去找他们
I've gotta go to them.
你要想出最好的方法
Decide you must how to serve them best.
你现在离开，可以帮助他们
If you leave now, help them you could...
但会破坏他们努力的目标
but you would destroy all for which they have fought and suffered.
我没有降落许可
No, I don't have a landing permit.
我找蓝多卡瑞辛
I'm trying to reach Lando Calrissian.
等一下，让我解释
Wait a minute! Let me explain!
不许偏离目前航道
You will not deviate from your present course.
- 脾气可真暴躁   - 你不是认识他吗？
- Rather touchy, aren't they? - I thought you knew this person.
隔太久了
That was a long time ago. I'm sure he's forgotten about that.
准许降落327平台
Permission granted to land on Platform 327.
谢谢
Thank you.
不用担心，我跟他是老交情
Nothing to worry about. We go way back, Lando and me.
谁担心啦？
Who's worried?
没半个人
No one to meet us.
不太对劲
I don't like this.
- 怎样才对劲？   - 降落倒是没问题
- What would you like? - They did let us land.
别担心，没问题的
Look, don't worry. Everything's gonna be fine.
相信我
Trust me.
看吧？ 我朋友来了
See? My friend.
眼睛睁亮点
Keep your eyes open.
嘿
Hey.
你这个龌龊，吃里扒外的下三滥
Why, you slimy, double-crossing, no-good swindler.
你还有胆回来见我？
You've got a lot of guts coming here, after what you pulled.
怎么样，老海盗？真高兴见到你
How you doin', you old pirate? So good to see you!
- 没想到有这么一天   - 好像很友善
- I never thought I'd see you again. - Well, he seems very friendly.
对，非常友善
Yes. Very friendly.
你来干嘛？
What are you doing here?
修船，我想请你帮忙
Repairs. I thought you could help me out.
- 我的船怎么啦？   - 你的船？
- What have you done to my ship? - Your ship?
你把它输给我了
Hey, remember, you lost her to me fair and square.
你好吗，秋巴卡？
How you doin', Chewbacca?
还在跟这家伙混？
Still hanging around with this loser?
哈，这位是谁？
Hello. What have we here?
欢迎，我是蓝多卡瑞辛，这里由我当家
Welcome. I'm Lando Calrissian. I'm the administrator of this facility.
- 是…？   - 莉亚
- And who might you be? - Leia.
欢迎，莉亚
Welcome, Leia.
够了…老滑头
All right, all right. You old smoothie.
我是C3PO，专长人类与机器人沟通…
Hello, sir. I am C-3PO, human-cyborg relations.
真是的！
My facilities are at your- Well, really!
- 千年鹰哪里有问题？   - 加速器
- What's wrong with the Falcon? - Hyperdrive.
- 我叫人检修    - 好
- I'll get my people to work on her. - Good.
这艘船救了我几次
That ship saved my life quite a few times.
银河里没人比它快
She's the fastest hunk of junk in the galaxy.
矿场怎么样？有赚头吗？
How's the gas mine? Still paying off for you?
没那么好赚，这里规模小，没法自给自足
Not as well as I'd like. We're a small outpost and not very self-sufficient.
补给问题很严重
I've had supply problems of every kind.
人手也缺…
I've had labour difficulties.
- 什么好笑的？   - 你啊
- What's so funny? - You. Listen to you.
口气像生意人，负责任的人
You sound like a businessman, a responsible leader.
当初谁能想到？
Who'd have thought that, huh?
你真是让我想起从前
Seeing you sure brings back a few things.
--
Yeah.
对，我现在有责任
Yeah, I'm responsible these days.
这是成功的代价
It's the price you pay for being successful.
有个熟面孔真好
Nice to see a familiar face.
真没礼貌！
How rude!
好像有个R2，不知道…
That sounds like an R2 unit in there.
哈？
I wonder if- Hello?
真有意思
How interesting.
- 你是谁？   - 哦，真是对不起
- Who are you? - Oh, my. I'm terribly sorry.
不是故意打扰，不，别起来…
I didn't mean to intrude. Please don't get up.
卢克，你还没出师
Luke, you must complete the training.
没办法，我要去救我朋友
I can't keep the vision out of my head. I've gotta help them.
你不能去
You must not go.
- 老韩跟莉亚会死掉   - 不能如此肯定
- But Han and Leia will die if I don't. - You don't know that.
连尤达都看不准
Even Yoda cannot see their fate.
但我能救他们，我能感觉到原力
But I can help them. I feel the Force.
但你无法控制它
But you cannot control it.
这是个危险的时刻
This is a dangerous time for you...
你容易被黑暗面诱惑
when you will be tempted by the dark side of the Force.
对，要听他的话
Yes, yes. To Obi-Wan you listen.
想想那个洞
The cave.
记得在洞里的事
Remember your failure at the cave.
但我后来有进步
But I've learned so much since then.
我保证会回来，把该学的学完
Master Yoda, I promise to return and finish what I've begun.
我向你保证
You have my word.
皇帝要的是你
It is you and your abilities the emperor wants.
因此才折磨你的朋友
That is why your friends are made to suffer.
所以我得赶去
That's why I have to go.
我不要你跟黑武士一样，成了皇帝的手下
Luke, I don't want to lose you to the emperor the way I lost Vader.
不会的
You won't.
要阻止他们，一切就靠这个
Stopped they must be. On this all depends.
唯有学成的绝地武士，有原力的辅助
Only a fully trained Jedi knight, with the Force as his ally...
才能打败黑武士和皇帝
will conquer Vader and his emperor.
你此时离开
If you end your training now...
你若选择走快捷方式，跟黑武士一样
if you choose the quick and easy path, as Vader did...
就会变成他们的爪牙
you will become an agent of evil.
要有耐心
Patience.
- 把老韩跟莉亚牺牲掉？   - 你尊重他们的目标，就得如此
- And sacrifice Han and Leia? - If you honour what they fight for...
是的
yes.
你若跟黑武士挑战，要独力战斗
If you choose to face Vader, you will do it alone.
我不能介入
I cannot interfere.
我了解
I understand.
R2，发动机器
R2, fire up the converters.
别沉溺于仇恨
Don't give in to hate.
否则会走向黑暗面
That leads to the dark side.
黑武士很厉害
Strong is Vader.
牢记已经学会的，它能保你的命
Mind what you have learned. Save you it can.
我会的
I will.
而且我会回来，我保证
And I'll return. I promise.
我早就说了，他很卤莽
Told you, I did. Reckless is he.
现在
Now...
更糟糕了
matters are worse.
他是唯一的指望
That boy is our last hope.
不，还有一个
No, there is another.
船快修好了，只差两三样东西
The ship's almost finished. Two or three more things and we're in great shape.
越快越好，有点不对劲
The sooner the better. Something's wrong here.
没人知道3PO下落
No one has seen or knows anything about 3PO.
它不可能只是迷路
He's been gone too long to have gotten lost.
放心
Relax.
我去跟蓝多打听
I'll talk to Lando and see what I can find out.
我不信任他
I don't trust Lando.
我也不信任他，但他是我朋友
Well, I don't trust him either, but he is my friend.
何况，我们就要走了
Besides, we'll soon be gone.
那表示你也要走了
Then you're as good as gone, aren't you?
怎么啦？
What happened?
哪里？
Where?
废料堆找到的？
Found him in a junk pile?
怎么会这样？阿秋，你会不会修？
What a mess. Chewie, you think you can repair him?
- 蓝多的手下会修   - 不要
- Lando's got people that can fix him. - No, thanks.
抱歉，是不是打扰了？
I'm sorry. Am I interrupting anything?
不会
Not really.
简直美极了
You look absolutely beautiful.
你属于这个云间城市
You truly belong here with us among the clouds.
谢谢
Thank you.
来吃点点心好吗？
Would you join me for a little refreshment?
大家一起来
Everyone's invited, of course.
机器人出了问题？
Having trouble with your droid?
没问题，为什么问呢？
No. No problem. Why?
我们规模很小
You see, since we're a small operation...
不受帝国的约束
we don't fall into the jurisdiction of the Empire.
- 你是公会成员？   - 也不是
- So you're part of the Mining Guild? - No, not actually.
没人注意我们
Our operation is small enough not to be noticed.
这样最好
Which is advantageous for everybody...
因为顾客也不想引人注意
since our customers are anxious to avoid attracting attention to themselves.
你不怕帝国发现，把你们关了？
Aren't you afraid the Empire's gonna find out, shut you down?
有这个危险，就像一朵云悬在天上
It's been a danger that looms like a shadow over everything we've built.
但现在我不怕了
But things have developed that'll ensure security.
我跟帝国谈妥了
I've just made a deal that'll keep the Empire out of here forever.
他们不会再烦我，请跟我们一起享用
We would be honoured if you would join us.
我是逼不得已，他们早一步到
I had no choice. They arrived right before you did.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我也很遗憾
I'm sorry too.
不，3PO跟他们一起
No, 3PO's with them.
等一下，马上就到了
Just hang on. We're almost there.
我不是故意打扰
I'm terribly sorry. I didn't mean to intrude.
不…别起来
No, please don't get up.
突击队？ 在这里？我们有危险了
Stormtroopers? Here? We're in danger.
快告诉其它人，糟糕！中弹了！
I must tell the others. Oh, no! I've been shot!
维达勋爵
Lord Vader.
等我抓到天行者
You may take Captain Solo to Jabba the Hutt...
韩苏洛就是你的人
after I have Skywalker.
他死掉就没用处了
He's no good to me dead.
他不会有大碍
He will not be permanently damaged.
维达勋爵，莉亚跟武技兽呢？
Lord Vader, what about Leia and the Wookiee?
别让他们离开这里
They must never again leave this city.
我们没说好，也没说把老韩交给他
That wasn't part of our agreement, nor was giving Han to this bounty hunter!
你说我亏待你？
Perhaps you think you're being treated unfairly?
没有
No.
那就好，不然我就派兵驻扎此地
Good. It would be unfortunate if I had to leave a garrison here.
这买卖越来越不利
This deal is getting worse all the time.
这样很好，我很喜欢
Oh, yes, that's very good. I like that.
不对，我看不见
Something's not right because now I can't see.
这样好多了
That's much better.
等一下…
Wait. Wait.
我的天！你怎么弄的？
Oh, my! What have you done?
怎么装反了？
I'm backwards!
真是个笨毛球
You flea-bitten furball!
拖把都比你聪明…
Only an overgrown mophead like you would be stupid enough-
我好难过
I feel terrible.
他们这是为什么？
Why are they doing this?
连问都没问一句
They never even asked me any questions.
- 蓝多，滚出去！   - 住嘴，听我说
- Get out of here, Lando. - Shut up and listen.
维达把莉亚跟阿秋交给我
Vader's agreed to turn Leia and Chewie over to me.
他们至少很安全
They'll have to stay here, but they'll be safe.
- 老韩呢？   - 交给那个赏金猎人
- And Han? - Vader's given him to the bounty hunter.
- 维达要我们死   - 他不要你们
- Vader wants us all dead. - He doesn't want you at all.
他要的人叫…天行者
He's after somebody called Skywalker.
- 维达设了陷阱   - 我们成了钓饵
- Lord Vader set a trap for him. - And we're the bait.
- 对，他已在路上   - 太好了
- He's on his way. - Perfect.
这下被你整惨了
You fixed us all real good, didn't you?
老友
My friend.
够了！
Stop!
我已经尽了力
I've done all I can.
很抱歉只能做到这样
Sorry I couldn't do better, but I got my own problems.
对
Yeah.
你是个大英雄
You're a real hero.
你待人接物有一套
You certainly have a way with people.
这设备很简陋
This facility is crude...
但应可将他
but it should be adequate to freeze Skywalker...
送到皇上面前
for his journey to the emperor.
维达勋爵，舰艇接近，X翼级舰
Lord Vader, ship approaching, X-wing class.
好，开始监视，让他降落
Good. Monitor Skywalker and allow him to land.
这是冻碳设备，不能用在人身上
Lord Vader, we only use this facility for carbon freezing. It might kill him.
我不能让他出差错
I do not want the emperor's prize damaged.
先拿韩苏洛试试
We will test it on Captain Solo.
把我的腿接上，就不会这么糗了
If you'd attached my legs I wouldn't be in this ridiculous position.
记住，秋巴卡，你要负责把我修好
Now remember, Chewbacca, you have a responsibility for me...
你可别做傻事
so don't do anything foolish.
怎么啦？
What's going on, buddy?
你要被抓去冻结
You're being put into carbon freeze.
他死了怎么办？ 他可值钱得很
What if he doesn't survive? He's worth a lot to me.
要是死了，帝国赔你。放进去
The Empire will compensate you if he dies. Put him in.
不要！不要！住手
Chewbacca, stop!
不要，阿秋！住手！听到没？
No, Chewie, stop!
住手！拜托你，不要！我还不想死
You're going to get us all killed! Yes, stop. I'm not ready to die.
喂，听我说
Hey! Hey! Listen to me.
阿秋，这样帮不了我
Chewie, this won't help me.
省点力气，以后还会碰头
Hey, save your strength. There'll be another time.
公主…
The princess.
就托你照顾了
You have to take care of her.
听到没有？
Do you hear me?
- 我爱你   - 我知道
- I love you. - I know.
怎么回事？ 转个身秋巴卡，我看不见
What's going on? Turn round. I can't see.
他被碳包住了
They've encased him in carbonite.
保护满周密的
He should be quite well-protected...
如果没被冻死的话
if he survived the freezing process, that is.
卡瑞辛，他是不是活着？
Well, Calrissian, did he survive?
还活着
Yes, he's alive.
在蛰伏状态
And in perfect hibernation.
就交给你了，赏金猎人
He's all yours, bounty hunter.
准备让天行者进去
Reset the chamber for Skywalker.
他刚降落，大臣
Skywalker has just landed, lord.
好，让他往这里走
Good. See to it that he finds his way in here.
卡瑞辛
Calrissian...
把公主押到我的舰上
take the princess and the Wookiee to my ship.
你叫他们留在这里
You said they'd be left under my supervision.
我要改变条件
I am altering the deal.
你可以祈祷不会再改变
Pray I don't alter it any further.
卢克！别进来！是个陷阱！
Luke, don't! It's a trap!
有陷阱！
It's a trap!
你有原力的辅助，天行者
The Force is with you, young Skywalker.
但你还称不上武士
But you are not a Jedi yet.
漂亮！
Well done.
把他们关在塔里，小声一点
Hold them in the security tower. And keep it quiet.
快
Move.
- 你要干嘛？   - 我们要走了
- What do you think you're doing? - We're getting out of here.
我早知道，一定是弄错了
I knew all along. It had to be a mistake.
你这样对老韩，我们还会信任你？
Do you think that after what you did to Han-
- 我是不得已   - 你干嘛？信任他！
- I had no choice. - What are you doing? Trust him!
我们了解，对不对？他是不得已
We understand, don't we, Chewie? He had no choice.
我只是想帮忙
I'm just trying to help.
我们不用你帮忙
We don't need any of your help.
-怎么啦？
What?
- 他好像说“老韩”   - 还有机会救老韩
- It sounds like Han. - There's still a chance to save Han...
在东侧平台
at the east... platform.
我真的很遗憾
I'm terribly sorry about all this.
毕竟他只是个武技兽
After all, he's only a Wookiee.
把韩苏洛放进货舱
Put Captain Solo in the cargo hold.
R2！你跑哪去了？
R2, where have you been?
转过去，你这个…
Wait. Turn around, you woolly-
快点！我们要救老韩
Hurry! We're trying to save Han from the bounty hunter.
至少你还是原来的你
Well, at least you're still in one piece.
你看我这模样
Look what's happened to me.
糟了，看你后面！
Oh, no! Chewie, they're behind you!
你进步不少，小伙子
You have learned much, young one.
我要让你一一见识
You'll find I'm full of surprises.
你跟我是一路的
Your destiny lies with me, Skywalker.
欧比王也会同意
Obi-Wan knew this to be true.
小儿科
All too easy.
皇上八成高估了你
Perhaps you're not as strong as the emperor thought.
不错
Impressive.
真是不错
Most impressive.
欧比王调教得好，你能控制恐惧
Obi-Wan has taught you well. You have controlled your fear.
现在…发出你的怒气
Now, release your anger.
这样才能打败我
Only your hatred can destroy me.
密码被改了
The security code has been changed.
R2，叫计算机越过安全系统
R2, you can tell the computer to override the security systems.
快点！
R2, hurry.
注意，我是蓝多卡瑞辛
Attention. This is Lando Calrissian. Attention.
帝国已经控制本城
The Empire has taken control of the city.
在大军抵达之间，大家请快离开
I advise everyone to leave before more imperial troops arrive.
这边
This way.
别怪我，我是个通译
Well, don't blame me. I'm an interpreter.
我哪知道那是电插座？
I'm not supposed to know a power socket from a computer terminal.
别管加速器，修好了
We're not interested in the hyperdrive on the Falcon. It's fixed!
开门啊，傻瓜！
Just open the door, you stupid lump!
我就知道你行，帅！
I never doubted you for a second. Wonderful!
啊，好痛 弯腰，没脑子的…
That hurts! Bend down, you thoughtless
莉亚，快走！
Go!
我以为会被害死
I thought that hairy beast would be the end of me.
当然好多了
Of course I've looked better.
你是我手下败将，抵抗也没用
You are beaten. It is useless to resist.
别跟欧比王一样被杀
Don't let yourself be destroyed as Obi-Wan did.
你跑不了
There is no escape.
别逼我杀你
Don't make me destroy you.
卢克，你不知道自己多重要
You do not yet realize your importance.
你才开始接触这力量
You have only begun to discover your power.
跟我学
Join me...
我让你出师
and I will complete your training.
你我若能合作
With our combined strength...
可以结束这场战争
we can end this destructive conflict...
使银河恢复秩序
and bring order to the galaxy.
我绝不跟你合作
I'll never join you!
你若知道黑暗面的力量
If you only knew the power of the dark side.
欧比王没告诉你，你父亲的下场
Obi-Wan never told you what happened to your father.
他跟我说了
He told me enough.
你杀了我父亲
He told me you killed him.
不，我就是你父亲
I am your father.
没这回事
That's not true.
不可能！
That's impossible!
你想想看，你知道事实如此
Search your feelings. You know it to be true.
你能杀掉皇帝，他也知道
You can destroy the emperor. He has foreseen this.
这是你命中注定
It is your destiny.
跟我一起
Join me...
我们父子可以统治银河
and together we can rule the galaxy as father and son.
跟我走
Come with me.
只有这条路
It is the only way.
班…
Ben.
Ben, please.
快听见
Hear me.
- 我们得回去   - 什么？
- We've got to go back. - What?
- 我知道卢克在哪   - 战机怎么办？
- I know where Luke is. - What about those fighters?
阿秋，照办
Chewie, just do it.
好…
All right, all right!
通知驱逐舰，我要上去了
Alert my Stardestroyer to prepare for my arrival.
看，上头有人
Look, someone's up there.
是卢克，阿秋，减速
It's Luke. Chewie, slow down.
到他底下，蓝多，打开顶舱门
We'll get under him. Lando, open the top hatch.
慢慢来，阿秋
Okay. Easy, Chewie.
- 蓝多？   - 可以了
- Lando? - Okay, let's go.
我们走
All right, Chewie. Let's go.
我就回来
I'll be back.
帝国驱逐舰
Stardestroyer.
阿秋，准备光速飞行
All right, Chewie. Ready for light speed.
如果加速器修好
If your people fixed the hyperdrive.
方位都设定好了，就看你的了
All the coordinates are set. It's now or never.
加速！
Punch it!
他们明明说修好了
They told me they fixed it.
我叫他们修的！
I trusted them!
不能怪我！
It's not my fault!
他们快被牵引光束锁定了
They'll be in range of our tractor beam in moments, lord.
加速器有没有关掉？
Did your men deactivate the hyperdrive on the Millennium Falcon?
--
- Yes, my lord. - Good.
好，准备登船，不要伤人
Prepare the boarding party and set your weapons for stun.
- 是，大人   - 副官！
- Yes, my lord. Lieutenant. - Yes, sir.
吵死了，怎么不用光速？
Noisy brute. Why don't we just go into light speed?
没办法？
We can't?
怎么知道加速器关掉了？
How would you know the hyperdrive is deactivated?
城里的计算机说的？
The city's central computer told you?
陌生计算机能信吗？
R2-D2, you know better than to trust a strange computer.
你小心点！
Ouch! Pay attention to what you're doing.
父亲…
Father.
孩子，跟我来
Son, come with me.
班
Ben.
你怎么不告诉我？
Why didn't you tell me?
是黑武士
It's Vader.
卢克，这是你命中注定
Luke, it is your destiny.
你怎么不告诉我？
Why didn't you tell me?
通知各单位，准备启动牵引光束
Alert all commands. Ready for the tractor beam.
R2，快给我回来，我还没装好
R2, come back at once! You haven't finished with me yet.
你不会修加速器，秋巴卡会修
You don't know how to fix the hyperdrive. Chewbacca can do it.
我这个模样，你还有空搞那个？
I'm standing here in pieces and you're having delusions of grandeur!
修好了！
You did it!
- 卢克，我们要起飞了   - 祝好运，蓝多
- Luke, we're ready for take-off. - Good luck, Lando.
我们找到贾霸再跟你联络
When we find Jabba the Hutt and that bounty hunter, we'll contact you.
在塔图因星的会合点见
I'll meet you at the rendezvous point on Tatooine.
公主，我保证找到老韩
Princess, we'll find Han. I promise.
阿秋，我等你的信号
Chewie, I'll be waiting for your signal.
你们俩保重
Take care, you two.
愿原力与你们同在
May the Force be with you.
谢
谢-*-观
赏